Guide to the Charles Astor Bristed Notebooks and Other Material
Yale University Library
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Yale Collection of American Literature
Charles Astor Bristed notebooks and other material
1838-1888
YCAL MSS 462
Bristed, Charles Astor, 1820-1874.
1.25 linear feet (3 boxes)
The collection contains seventeen notebooks from Bristed's undergraduate and graduate studies at Yale and Cambridge universities from the late 1830s to mid 1840s, chiefly on classical authors and texts, including translations, and mathematics, as well as a catalog of his books, several letters, a diary, a receipt, and two printed books, including Bristed's Anacreontics, published under the pseudonym Carl Benson.
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library P. O. Box 208240 New Haven, CT 06520-8240 Email: beinecke.library@yale.edu Phone: (203) 432-2972 Fax: (203) 432-4047
Administrative Information
Provenance
Purchased from Howard S. Mott Rare Books, 1964.
Information about Access
This collection is open for research.
Charles Astor Bristed (1820-1874)
Charles Astor Bristed, author, was the son of Reverend John Bristed and Magdalen Astor, daughter of John Jacob Astor II. He was born in New York City and educated at home by tutors before attending Yale University (1835-1839) and the University of Cambridge (1840-1845). Following his studies at Cambridge and some travel in Europe, he returned to the United States and began writing, sometimes under the name of Carl Benson. Under this pseudonym he was a regular contributor to the sporting journals Porter's Spirit of the Times and Wilkes's Spirit of the Times. Published works include: Selections from Catullus (1849); A Letter to the Hon. Horace Mann (1850); The Upper Ten Thousand: Sketches of New York Society (1852); Five Years in an English University (1852); Pieces of a Broken-Down Critic (1858); The Interference Theory of Government (1867); Anacreontics (1872); and On Some Exaggerations in Comparative Philology (1873).
In 1847 Bristed married Laura Brevoort of New York, who died in 1860. In 1867 he married Grace Sedgwick of Lenox, Massachusetts.
Biographical information taken from "Charles Astor Bristed." Dictionary of American Biography. New York: Charles Scribner's Sons, 1936. Gale Biography in Context. (accessed 3 May 2011).
Description of the Papers
The collection contains seventeen notebooks from Bristed's undergraduate and graduate studies at Yale and Cambridge universities from the late 1830s to mid 1840s, chiefly on classical authors and texts, including translations, and mathematics, as well as a catalogue of his books, several letters, a diary, a receipt, and two printed books, including Bristed's Anacreontics, published under the pseudonym Carl Benson.
Arrangement
Organized into two series: I. Notebooks, 1838-1846. II. Other Material, 1841-1888.
Access Terms
This collection is indexed under the following access points in Orbis, the Yale University Library online catalog.
Subjects
Bristed, Charles Astor, 1820-1874.; Yale College (1718-1887) --Students.; University of Cambridge --Students.; American literature --19th century.; Authors, American --19th century --Archives.
Authors
Bristed, Charles Astor, 1820-1874.
Occupations and Functions
Authors.
Collection Contents
- Notebooks, 1838-1846; Series I.; 1.25 linear feet (3 boxes)
  Arranged alphabetically by title.
  Series I. Notebooks contains seventeen notebooks from Bristed's undergraduate and graduate studies at Yale and Cambridge universities from the late 1830s to mid 1840s, chiefly on classical authors and texts, including translations, and mathematics, as well as a catalogue of his books.
  - "Aristophanes...", undated (Box 1)
  - "Aristotle's politics (with Gibbs Solus, Blakesley's and Thompson's lectures)", 1845-1846 (Box 1)
  - "Books of the Republic", 1845 (Box 1)
  - "Catalogue of books belonging to C. A. Bristed", undated (Box 1)
  - "Cicero... Sophocles... general notes", 1842 (Box 1)
  - "Composition", 1844 (Box 1)
  - "Extracts for translation with notes", undated (Box 1)
  - "Extracts Vol. I Polymigia No. 2", 1838-1839, undated (Box 1)
  - "Freshman subjects", 1840-1841 (Box 2)
  - "Life of Thucydides", undated (Box 2)
  - [Notes in Latin and Greek], undated (Box 2)
  - [Notes on mathematics], undated; 2 folders (Box 2)
  - [Notes on reading the classics], undated (Box 2)
  - "Optics, trigonometry, dynamics", undated (Box 2)
  - "Scripta delecta Vol. 2 Part 1", 1839 (Box 2)
  - [Translations], undated (Box 2)
  - [Translations], undated (Box 3)
  - "Whewell's lectures", 1844-1846 (Box 3)
- Other Material, 1841-1888; Series II.; (5 folders)
  Arranged alphabetically by material type.
  Series II. Other Material contains several letters, a diary, a receipt, and two printed books, including Bristed's Anacreontics, published under the pseudonym Carl Benson. Correspondence includes four letters to Bristed, from Richard Grant White and others, and one autograph letter from Bristed to an unidentified recipient.
  - Correspondence, 1863-1888, undated (Box 3)
  - Diary, 1856-1857 (Box 3)
  - Receipt, 1841 January 20 (Box 3)
  - Anacreontics, printed version, with inscription, 1872-1873 (Box 3)
  - A Dictionary of English Etymology by Hensleigh Wedgwood, printed version, with autograph notes, 1862-1863 (Box 3)